Okay, thank you.
So, like many Buddhist classes,
um
this is a
kind of a depressing class.
Um the desire
uh to stop our future lives and the
anticipations of taking future lives.
And um
there's a misperception
or a misinterpretation in Buddhism about
this subject. Um regarding future lives,
uh
a lot of people come to this conclusion,
well,
this life isn't working out for me.
It's just not working. Uh the karmas are
not really helping and I'll just bank on
my next life and just project my actions
toward my next life.
And that's in our really in our
philosophical uh thinking incorrect.
You want to get out of this uh future
lifespan, this cycle. You want to remove
yourself from this uh
endless suffering of the samsaric
circles that we create on a everyday
basis.
And so, um
part of the idea of stopping the desire
for future lives entails the three
principal paths. And primarily, we can
focus on the renunciation and the
realization of we're tired.
Uh we must get out on this this
lifetime. We do not want to do this
again.
It's almost like the disgust becomes an
obsession and we prove every day that
life is suffering.
And we prove that the aspects of the
Four Noble Truths are real every day
when we get up.
And so
I've read the reading, you know, I
didn't know I was going to do this until
today. So, I I I did a fast track
reading of the com- of the actual
commentary. And the verses are
beautiful. I suggest that you read some
of them. They're the reading is really
lovely and it it's
I'm going to read some of the verses and
then we'll talk about it. And um
and and and and really the the crux of
the course of this class is to stop the
desire for having a future lives.
Uh
and here we go.
Um so
think over and over how deeds and their
fruits never fail.
And the cycles of suffering never fail.
We must stop the desire for our future
lives.
Um so in that context, right? the desire
for the future We we normally think, you
know, I hope my future births can can
really get into a realm that's going to
be pleasurable. And we have this kind of
understanding of
death, you know, the death in the
realms. We know that there different
realms of existences, right? How many
know that that that course?
Yeah. So
we're in the desire realm, correct?
Uh and then there's a form and formless
realm.
And in within the desire realm, we have
different aspects that uh include lower
than human and higher than human.
And you know
we're not animals. We're not hungry
ghosts. We're not in lower hell realms,
hot or cold hell realms. We're not in
demigod or pleasure realms, which are
uh in this realm, but also invisible
beings who live in those realms.
But, interesting
in our context of of wanting to be born
in one of those realms
is also this feeling that we're going to
in a sense be removed from our
suffering.
We really want to be born in one of
these realms in certain traditions.
We actually have meditations to actually
design to be born in one of those higher
realms.
A lot of meditations are designed to go
to what we call the form or formless
realms, which are
extremely pleasurable and very, very
in life years, millions of years.
Um
we kind of relate it sometimes to
the Christian heaven.
This idea of eternal heaven.
But, we know in our in our teachings,
and we know in the in the in the
teachings of the wheel of life that
these these
these realms will completely end into a
lower rebirth. It's guaranteed. Because
the amount of merit to stay in these
realms is so enormous.
And you're not truly creating a
continuation of your merit to stay
there.
And so, ultimately you fall into a much
lower realm.
And then we say the human desire uh
realm is probably the the launchpad and
the best instrument to get enlightened
in one lifetime. To remove the
suffering. To remove the idea that
future realms could potentially give me
an advantage or more pleasure
or more promise.
Uh but, that's not the case. We don't
want to go there.
So, to get this idea of I'm tired is the
first major step, the first
understanding that renunciation has to
be the cornerstone
to begin the work in this lifetime to
get out in this lifetime.
Um
And so
in the process of karma we must learn
the correlations of of karma and how it
functions.
And I think Connie um
did a great job on the PowerPoint again.
Thank you, love.
So
So the laws of karma, who can tell me
the first one?
Yeah, you can say like it makes like. Um
the idea that you plant a seed uh you
know, to find a partner and then you do
the four steps and then hopefully with
the right motivation and the
fertilization of different rejoicing
components brings you that partner.
The mailman delivers it. The mailwoman
delivers it to you. Guaranteed. Similar
result.
You take care of lonely people. It's
It's It's It's a component. It's the the
the actual action that will create the
seeds for you to find the partner.
And it's not that simple.
There are very subtle parts to all of
this.
You know, what is your intention and
what are the components of the intention
that you're about to embark on in
creating a seed. So in that sense uh you
know, we keep it basic in DCI and we
say, you know, you plant watermelon
seeds, you're going to get watermelons.
You you know, do a banana plantation,
you get bananas. You're not going to
get, you know, artichokes.
Like makes like.
And it you know, the
of karma
um I said earlier today to a lot of you
that were here that it's more subtle
than understanding emptiness.
That the tapestry of weaving karmic
seeds um
can be designed for your future. You can
design what you want to walk into 6
months from now, a year from now,
six years from now, 12 years from now.
You are doing it whether you're
conscious of it or not in this room
right now.
So, let's do it consciously and create
what we want and what we want to avoid.
It's It's so important to kind of
I don't know, sit back and understand
that your seeds got you in this room
for countless lifetimes maybe.
These seeds are so extraordinary in this
room.
You found
the Dharma in this room.
Somehow or another, you you know, all of
us should do this. Congratulations.
Thank you very much to Josephine or Joe
from my past karmic seeds.
I finally got to the Diamond Mountain
University school for uh
for the ultimate goal.
For seeing emptiness directly and
ultimate final enlightenment.
So, we must have planted remarkable
seeds.
Do we remember them?
I don't know. I I I don't, you know, I
don't I don't know my past lives. I
don't spend much time thinking about
them.
We live in a town where there's more
past life regression therapists
than New York City. You just go to the
Whole Foods bulletin board and there's
like six people that will
hypnotically bring you back and give you
some kind of like, you know, a moment of
a past life. It doesn't interest me, but
people like it and it it may help
someone. I don't know.
So, like makes like and
that is such a quintessential Eureka.
Like, it's a
Okay, I get it.
Watermelons make watermelons. My god.
That's simple and elegant. And let's not
complicate it.
And then a four-step program or a
four-step idea can guide you into the
proof of that.
And we always say when we're on tour,
how many people that show up in a 2,000
room
uh auditorium will actually take this
home and and do the litmus test, will
actually try it.
We think it's less than 10%.
That people hear it and like it,
but there's some other seed in their
minds that don't allow them to actually
embark on the adventure of seeing if it
really works.
And then you come back next year the the
following city and
at the break we're all standing there to
answer questions and somebody will come
up and say like, I tried it.
I have I found my partner.
Or I actually turned my business around
or
all of the above. You know, it and it In
that moment you've done your job. You
know, they remember that you were in
front of them the year before and they
just want to tell you in this beautiful
rejoicing way that
that karmic correlation of doing the
four steps functioned and they got what
they wanted.
And
in a way, uh
that's the reward the teacher
can really be be
you know, in a good way proud of.
Because that that was a life-changing
moment for that person and you so your
seed saw them be happy about that.
They're going to work it because if it
worked once, it will work over and over
and over.
And
these laws are a foundation to all of
our lives to consciously plant our
future.
The we gave you the what the four forces
yesterday or today or was I'm sure I'm
losing track of time.
Uh which is the antidote to lessen the
results of our negative karma or remove
the obstacles. Another cornerstone of
fundamental Buddhist ideals and ideas
and proofs.
Um
So yes, like makes like.
Good results come from good deeds, bad
results come from bad deeds.
Comfort to know there are laws.
Who makes them? Without laws, chaos.
Farmer plants corn and pineapples come
up.
Next slide.
So karma increases exponentially.
Um
Geshe La likes to use this uh uh
idea that
he calls it the waiter's test.
If a waiter doesn't understand a word
that you mention,
don't use it. So I would when I was
looking at the word exponentially, I
thought, how many people if you went to
a restaurant next week and you basically
said something like, you know, can you
exponentially scramble my eggs a little
bit more quickly?
Will they understand that?
And it it's true. What would be a better
word to say other than exponentially?
Maybe expand? That's an easier word to
Does it give the same
explosive explodes Um, the idea uh
when we taught this course in 2017 of
January
I think it was you Stanley. I guess you
Michael said, "Okay, if karma expands
every 24 hours twice, doubles
how many seeds will you plant in a
four-step program?" Like if you pull
together an idea and you plant the seed,
you do the first step, you find a person
who wants the same thing, you just do it
and you do your rejoicing.
Uh, it should exponentially double every
day.
And when I don't know when you did the
numbers, it was 31 trillion at day 24.
Some of you know, outrageous number of
the exponential expansion of of karmic
seeds. Um, the idea that our seeds right
now are ripening at 65 a second. Which
is creating what?
Every aspect of your conscious reality.
Using the senses, but also the mind.
Everything you're thinking, everything
you're seeing, smelling, tasting,
touching.
Everything.
Pleasant, unpleasant, neutral,
indifferent.
It's all happening in 65, like a movie.
And in a good meditation, what happens?
You can slow the movie down.
Really slowly.
And potentially start to see it's moving
and projecting out to watch the reality
happen before your very eyes.
It's possible.
It's one of the real reasons to
meditate.
Couldn't you can you catch the seed
opening and creating your reality.
It's possible.
And all of you will do it someday.
So, the exponential factor of seeds
makes the whole wonderful, remarkable,
karmic possibility what?
Possible. Now, um think about it. If I
plant a seed by giving
um
I don't know, maybe Chönyi, you know,
Geshe Michael's giving tons of $100
bills away.
Why is he doing that?
I mean, where does a recipient of maybe,
you know, a third of my annual income?
I mean,
because, you know, why? Why is he doing
this? What's What's his
personal,
you know,
motivation?
Well, he's showing us, number one, the
exponential factor. If he's giving $100
away in in in a DCI tour, he's
guaranteeing in two to five weeks he'll
get a thousand bucks.
You know, he makes it very clearly
simplified.
But,
I don't know. I I often think, well, you
know, basically what he's doing is
really
we talk about endowments for our
nonprofits.
Like, how In 10 years, could we raise
five or ten million dollars?
You know, to make our diamond mountain
secure, make ACIP secure, ACI having
some kind of a wonderful,
you know, nest egg that we don't worry
about spending our precious time raising
money.
You know, theoretically, this is what I
came up with, that that's one of his
modus operandi.
And so, when he's on tour, he'll give
thousands of dollars away. Now, he's
giving $300 to people in the audience.
Um and it it it is this idea that seeds
will exponentially double every single
day if you know what to do.
And
I don't know. The sky's the limit here.
Like
what what do you want?
Well, I don't know. I'm I want I want to
stick around and see what happens for
the next 25 years.
You know.
Come on. Like
this is the most exciting thing on the
planet to me.
Um
you know,
our beautiful minds waking up to the
possibility of changing
exponentially the seeds of the planet.
To perceive a much more what?
Harmonious
world.
It's not looking so good out there in my
in my seed
you know, projected life. It feels a
little bit threatening as a matter of
fact. And so we as practitioners, if we
understand the exponential factor of
planting seeds that you're doing 65
a second.
Wow.
Think of the factor of change and
possibility if we do it much more
consciously.
Much more um
I don't know um for the benefit of
others like
how do we begin the practice of planting
the seeds
for not just our own self-interest, but
for the benefit of as many people as we
can imagine?
For the benefit of those who are
planting seeds in the wrong way
and getting results that are creating a
lot of violence in our world.
Um
you get the idea, I think, right?
I mean, now we're talking
uh nuclear power here. We're talking a
small seed of a thought
going through the mind every single
what? Second? There's thoughts going
through the mind.
What would happen if you begin to
control that factor?
Or you canceled out the thoughts that
are creating negative possibilities in
your reality?
Because it's not like this big wheel
going round samsara, you know, this
the 12 links of dependent origination,
you know.
It's just going around and you're caught
in it. Well, yeah, we're all caught in
it. We're definitely caught in it. But
it's these thousands of tiny little mini
samsaras that we're creating on a daily
basis.
They're little tiny seeds
that you know, begin to manifest in
unpleasant forms.
Pick your flavor.
Um
I don't know. I I'm getting We had a
Pilates class today. It was like like a
tune-up for me. It was like fantastic.
Like my body was achy from the other two
classes.
But for some reason the Pilates things
kicked in and I I felt like I just got
like an a lube and an oil kind of, you
know, checkup and my god, some kind of
beautiful seeds ripened in that class.
Um where did that come from?
Teaching, you know, tough ass classes in
in different places. Um I I I love to
teach yoga because I think it's one of
the exponential factors for becoming a
great meditator cuz it's dealing with
subtle mind and body.
And so, you know, to have a result like
that happen uh is so beautiful. You
know, you can I can bank on that being a
component of when I was teaching maybe
um a month and a half or 2 months ago
at SCIM.
Um so, we have to learn this system and
we have to begin to practice it. We have
to begin to meditate on
uh these karmic correlations.
Next.
So, there's this idea also that if you
didn't do karma, you'll never get a
meter result.
Um
this is interesting because it gets into
expectations,
the disappointments in life.
You know,
um
the links that
how many disappointments have we had in
the last, I don't know, year?
I have a few,
but why? Why do we have like
expectations that we assume will happy
happen if we do certain things?
But then we get disappointed when they
don't.
Um because we didn't plant the seed for
it.
It didn't work.
Um
as simplified as the four steps are,
it's the most elegant, you know,
formula. It's almost like a mathematical
theory of relativity.
It functions and it's easy
and it's uncomplicated.
And it works.
And so, we can't be disappointed when we
don't get what we want. We can't be
disappointed when the expectation that
should arrive and it doesn't happen,
we shouldn't get disappointed because we
didn't plant the seed.
Um and so, this is this is what
comes about if you didn't do the karma,
you'll never meet the result.
And um
there's a debate in my mind about that
because as we're doing 65 a second right
now, right?
Are we also creating karmas at the same
time?
Sure, we are.
We're creating karmas right now.
It's happening right now. Result.
More karmas.
Right after.
There's only a tiny moment of change
when when another karma is created.
We create karmas
with body, speech, and mind, right?
We We create karmas in our actions. We
create karmas with our speech. We create
karmas with our thoughts. Which Which
are the most powerful?
Yeah, our thinking. It gets us in the
most
trouble.
And
I know the 3-year retreat was one of
these like amazing eye-openers about how
the functioning of patterns of thoughts
in my mind
um were so hardwired into uh
subtle consciousness that they weren't
in the front end format of my constant
thinking process. They were just behind
it.
They were just behind this veil.
And it would be funny because I'd be do
I I wouldn't be in deep subtle
mindfulness.
I'd be washing the dishes. And then
suddenly I would see the watcher's mind
watching a pattern of thought systems
that I've had for 50 years.
That was actually creating suffering in
my life. I was like, "Oh my god, I've
been judging that person for like 45
years."
And it started when was 17, and I
remember when that happened. You start
to actually begin to unveil patterns of
thinking
that are always going on just behind the
radar of your conscious mind.
And that's cool.
Because when that begins to happen,
you're beginning to erase that pattern
for good because you just brought it to
the conscious mind.
And you're seeing the results of
suffering in a mini samsaric cycle
that's been going on for
three or four decades.
So, those were more important moments in
a way in in my three-year retreat than,
you know, these deep subtle other places
that happen in in meditation. But
without the meditation, would I have
that result?
I don't think so.
You see, it's resulting in the so-called
conventional world of ordinary things,
washing dishes,
driving a car,
um
having that Mahamudra watchdog
meditation on our thought process is not
something we just do for 45 minutes on
the cushion. We do it in our world.
We're We're always mindful of what the
processes are, of how we're interpreting
our reality.
So, the third law of karma is this
neutralizing aspect of if you don't
plant the seed, you're just not ever
going to get a result.
And we've all been there many times of,
you know, why didn't I get the promotion
at work or, you know,
why can't I afford, you know,
a two-week vacation in Bali?
Why can't, you
I don't know.
All the above. We're, you know, just
think of the things that we would like
or expect to get or have that we don't
get or have.
Um
There's something that we call oxygen
money in the in the Diamond Cutter
system. It's a very beautiful idea.
And it's about having money so the mind
doesn't have to worry about it.
That it's just
in the background that you can sleep at
night and know
it's okay. I'm planting oxygen money.
You know, I'm not going to, you know,
I'm not interested in making
millions of dollars. I'm interested in
being comfortably sound to not worry
about financial burden.
And that I love that because
if you're planting seeds and and and
Connie, my wife is like so good with
this. Uh
I'm like always like, "Okay, we better
double down over here, you know."
You know, we better give more, you know,
and I'm saying, "We don't we can't
afford it, you know."
But she's right. Like just double down
and just let it go and and rejoice that
you had enough cash to give to Diamond
Mountain in your wallet, you know,
because you want to keep the seeds going
to be here. So, oxygen money is cool.
You can actually
relieve the fact that the
behind-the-scenes anxiety or the thing
before you go to bed about not paying
your bills is gone forever
because you're banking on a karmic
level.
You're planting the seeds and you're
banking on a karmic level. It's no
longer throwing money in a savings
account.
And that is just a beautiful function of
karma
if you know how to do it.
Um
So, next
Geshe Michael Roach Misawa, "Good news,
you cannot avoid the results of your
good deeds."
That's a nice thought, right? "Good
news, you cannot avoid the results of
your good deeds." Well, it's not so good
news because you can't avoid the results
of your bad deeds, either.
Um
you know,
um we like to accentuate the positive,
right?
But, we also have to realize that, you
know,
um
in the karmic course, we talk about
dirty white seeds or stained karmic
seeds.
There's always some aspect in our
process of consciously creating karmic
seeds
that has um
it has we we grasp, we know we want some
result, you know? We want it. We want
this
I don't know.
Yeah, we can do all the, you know,
there's something called
uh the three spheres of giving.
You know, the giver is empty and the
action of giving is empty and the
receiver is empty and, you know, we get
profoundly
involved in the emptiness of the three
aspects of giving.
And that's great, you know, but
in the back of your mind, at least mine
is like, "Okay,
6 months I'll have another 6,000 bucks,
you know?"
I don't know, there's something there
that makes the karma stained. There's
still this in
interested grasping to know
Yeah,
you know, I'm going to get a result.
Um
and it's stained. So,
in in in that course, we say
very few people can create perfect
seeds.
Aryas and above.
Um
that the idea of the essence of
emptiness of everything that we do
has to be exponentially very high with
the actual practice of seed planting.
Whether it's, you know,
uh
giving things away to get money or
whatever the component is, we have to
really understand emptiness.
That also is charging it, not just
rejoicing in in the process of doing it.
If the higher you understand emptiness,
the much more powerful the seed is going
to be planted.
And uh
yeah, it's it's a it's a process that we
learn.
Um
what about the objects that we choose
to generate seeds guaranteed to give us
good results?
Say it again.
Yeah, give me an example of a high
object.
Say it again.
Okay, a teacher. An authentic teacher,
yeah. W- What else would be a a
a a high object?
Say it.
Parents, who said parents?
Yeah, parents.
What about ACI or Diamond Mountain?
Or ACIP, yeah, remember? Yeah.
ACIP Russia especially.
Yeah, I mean, it's funny. Uh
we, you know,
we don't
in our in our system of
high comic objects,
um
we people do their due diligence when
they give money away. It's like an
investment. At at least people that feel
that if you give a dollar to ACIP a day,
um
you're in some way saving
some part of a system that's bringing
the ancient manuscripts to an end result
of a translation of a page of data that
would normally be hidden for hundreds of
years, but suddenly that dollar goes to
India and a woman inputs that page and
it ends up in Sedona and a translator
takes that page and translates it and
makes
another commentary on karma.
So, that process is fascinating. You get
the merit of that
with your dollar, you see.
You get
You're indirectly getting 10% to
guarantee that the wisdom of whatever
that's going to bring forth into the
world in our language that you
understand.
You'll get that karma.
You'll get the wisdom from that page
that you paid for.
A dollar I think it's a $1.29 a page I
figured out for everything that we input
um from start to finish.
um
And that's
not including inflation of the Indian
rupee, which is like 70 right now. Uh
everybody's complaining about it and I
I'm like
Okay, everybody gets raises.
Um but you see the
the investment you make with a conscious
contribution or um
a service to your teacher, a service to
uh some noble cause.
Uh
it doesn't have to be about saving
texts. It can be
about, I don't know, Doctors Without
Borders. They do amazing work. Uh any
any component that's serving humanity
has a high karmic relationship to your
action to give.
If you are if you want to give
something.
And so, um
karmic objects we have to think about,
um
I I think the other thing that is very
interesting karmically is
the reluctance to pay taxes in our world
is interesting, right? That we don't
want to part with my my money to pay
taxes.
And um
there's a great
talent of people that know how to create
loopholes to avoid paying taxes.
Uh
and um
you know,
that has to do also with the correlation
of honesty with the integrity of knowing
that
um
you are responsible for every aspect
that's legal in your system, wherever
you are in the world,
because, you know, the karma of creating
uh an illicit system to avoid paying
what the responsible aspect of a citizen
should be doing for their country
will bounce back and kick you in a in a
way that is really serious.
So, we have to learn correlations of
karma. We have to understand the
components of
the subtleties of how we actually think
about
um doing the actions of these four
amazing steps.
So, let's keep going.
It's funny.
There's certain times in life with karma
also. Uh Maria was telling me and
telling us today about how
all of these seeds ripened in her life.
She had no desire to become an ACI
teacher. She had no desire to follow
this path. But within a two-month period
millions of seeds ripened and suddenly
her life is transformed in a single
two-month period.
And that happens in many parts of our
lives. We meet a partner and get
married. Boom, change of life. We have a
child, change of life.
Um
we get the job of our dreams, change of
life.
You know, these these build-ups of
beautiful karmic seeds that suddenly
burst into your reality and change
everything about what it is for you.
And it also has to do with the point of
death.
Because
in the process of death
what happens to your seeds?
What actually is going on?
What's happening inside karmically to
your reality?
Everything is running out.
Seeds are popping like crazy.
Your world is actually being destroyed.
Your senses are closing down. All the
seeds to see, hear, taste, touch, and
feel, and think are dying.
Running out in this lifetime.
And so,
uh
this comes into the whole point of what
seed will take you. What karma is going
to take you
into
the process of what?
Your next rebirth. I mean, essentially,
um
And this is where we have to really work
hard on our karmic seeds.
Why?
Yeah.
Uh
Geshe Michael's
teacher used to watch the New York State
Lottery on Wednesday nights because it
used to be milli- I'm sure it's millions
of dollars more, but And there there
used to be a beautiful girl in a short
mini skirt, and she would come out on
the stage,
you know, and smile, and they'd play all
this, you know, happy music, and they
had these air air systems where these
balls, like ping pong balls, are
rolling, and then she'd push a button,
and a number would come up, right? And
then the number would be read, and, you
know, they'd have like 45 million
viewers like waiting to hear the number.
But he always said,
"That's what's going to happen."
When those seeds are finalizing, and
that last seed ripens, that's taking you
to your next rebirth.
Do you know where you're going?
You see.
Where is that going to take you?
And are you going to be fully engaged
with the controlling of that at the
point of the process of death? And that
to me is probably one of the most
fascinating things that I am obsessed
about. Maybe it has to do with my age, I
don't know. But
it had to do a lot with the 3-year
retreat as well. So,
the karmas of not the uncertainty, it
now brings us to more depressing news.
And uh we have some slides to tell you
about that.
So, the good news is there's only three
questions to your homework today. So,
that's pretty easy and all the answers
are being told to you right now.
So, life has no certainty or no
security. Everything is totally
unreliable. No plan is fail-safe.
Well, that's depressing.
Isn't it?
You should say, "No, because I know the
four steps. I can design my future."
Of course, it's not.
I know exactly how to navigate that. I
can do it.
We have 18 courses and then another 18
courses and then we have other things
that will guarantee that we can kill
this idea.
We can kill it for for this life and
beyond.
But,
for the meantime,
do you agree that life has no certainty
and no security?
Yeah. I don't know if I'm going to wake
up tomorrow morning.
I'm not sure. I I can't guarantee it. I
don't have any premonitional moments of
clairvoyance to say, you know, "Tomorrow
morning at 8:00 you're going to have a
heart attack after eating
uh the fruit at the Jason Kupfer
Center." I don't have No, I don't have
that.
I I It'd be great in a way, right? To
know.
And there are meditations to say, "Why
don't you sit down on the cushion
tomorrow morning at 8:00 and then
take a meditation to say, 'You know
what? At 11:00 it's my last breath.'"
Why don't I do a meditation on my death?
Why don't we give death some space of
certainty
in our practice?
Why don't we actually sit on the cushion
and do a death meditation and say, "You
know what?
What would happen if suddenly at 10:45
tonight
um is my last breath?"
It's fun
to get put the
put the code on of death
and start thinking about the possibility
that it could happen much more
realistically than how we perceive it
conceptually.
You know, I'm still thinking, you know,
well, you know,
I'm healthy, you know, I can do a good
yoga practice and we eat well,
you know,
uh I have Medicare, I can go to any
doctor.
Um
but come on.
You know, I have another 10 years. I I I
know I do.
It's certain.
It's not. We don't. And we just have to
get used to that and fit
put it on.
Start to feel the the sense that could
it be possible that tomorrow morning at
8:00 a.m. I don't wake up?
And practice with it and own it and it's
actually so liberating. It creates
something It creates a mind space that
is almost like a freedom that your fear
or your back primal beginningless death
birth system
begins to be eliminated. It opens
something up in your mind stream. It's
very beautiful.
Um so, in your toolkit, you should have
a really good death meditation
or a couple
um because
we don't know where we're going to go.
We might as well like look at it now.
Um
the there's something in our system
called the fourth flower in the DCI
system and we have the four flowers and
uh it's the results of our karmic seeds,
right?
And the last one is that we are
literally designing what we're walking
into after the in the future, which is
implied cuz we don't talk about
reincarnation.
Uh our future life.
And um
And it's kind of beautiful in a way, the
fourth flower. The third flower is
creating this beautiful reality here in
this room.
Uh you're walking into your everyday
existence by your seeds and it's it's
it's an enormous beautiful possibility
of
what do I love about it and what I don't
like about it and what I can change that
I don't like about it with seed planting
systems and the four forces.
Um
but about the future life.
Can we design it?
Well, we first want to get enlightened
in one lifetime. We first want to have
the direct perception of emptiness in
this lifetime.
And if you're here in the room,
I I think you're more than 50% home.
Honestly, I really believe that.
Um
I just
I you know, I bought I I took the
Kool-Aid and I bought the package and I
really believe it's possible that all of
you in this room have the potential in
this lifetime
to get out of the wheel
and have a few maybe future rebirths
before you're completely gone and
finished.
It's possible.
We have to make space in our hearts for
that. We have to understand that
the habituation of countless beginning
lives
are pushing us against that. We don't
believe it. We're hardwired to think
that's not possible.
So, it's it's cool to start redesigning,
you know, your your your thinking that
way. That none of us in this room
uh
don't have this possibility. If you're
here, and Geshe Michael has said it
twice, I think, since we've taught the
the training and the teachings of Lam
Rim, that if you're here,
you're one in a million or one in 10
million. And you got to like
you've got to take the Kool-Aid.
You've got to believe it. I I believe
it, and I think I want you to kind of
think about it more. Um
there's always, in my world, a
hesitation to
uh to come to Diamond Mountain.
Even now, I mean, I lived here for 3 and
1/2 years, but even now, there's this
backwater mind of mine. Seeds are
popping to say, you know,
it's always a bit of a gauntlet. You
know what a gauntlet is? Like a
it's always there's some karma that will
ripen unexpectedly when I hit this land.
And there's some karma that is
unpleasant that I begin to feel when I'm
here
that I have to go through. And uh
it's always been there in the even
after, you know,
all of I what I've done here and and
what we've done in three-year retreat.
And um
that happened again when I arrived. I I
just gotten off a plane, and that I
could excuse the
you know, the discomfort of coming here
and and the jet lag, but um
there are seeds that ripen here for me.
I don't know if that that's for you, but
there are seeds that ripen here for me
that uh
feel uncomfortable because I'm going
into this
other aspect of myself and
I don't know. The perception of seeds
for Diamond Mountain is that it's
extremely powerful.
For me.
And
I can ripen things here that
good, bad, or indifferent I will I will
allow to happen. And and those seeds are
either extraordinary or something that I
have to correct or fix.
And maybe after the second day, it's
just amazing.
Like something shifts and we're here
together. We're hearing great teachings
and I wouldn't want to be anywhere else
on the planet.
But there is something interesting how
powerful
this place
which I believe um took 15 years to
purify and
you know, has created something
extraordinary just being here
karmically for all of us
um
can change your mind.
So, take advantage of it, you know.
You know, I I'm I'm I'm just saying
karmically you're at the right kind of
place at the right time with the right
components of your seeds to go deeper.
And take advantage of that. Bring
yourself to the cushion more and more
when you're here.
I think things can ripen quicker. The
time gap that we talked about earlier
can just be
quickened. Things can ripen in certain
places faster and this is one of them, I
believe.
So.
Um
in order to escape the circle of life,
one must take up
uh
beautiful white actions, plant good
seeds, and abandon black actions. We
must believe in the laws of actions and
consequences all the time.
And to do this, we must contemplate upon
the actions and consequences.
That's a formal way of saying
practice the four aspects of karma, the
four laws.
There's another aspect that's the
downside that's depressing
about negative seeds and deeds
and um
in the realms of existence, there are
lower realms. And
you know, the the whole philosophy of
Buddhism
uh
talk about, you know, the hell realms,
the cold realms of hell, the warm realms
of hell,
the hungry ghost realms, right? The
animal realms, um
and of course, the human and the demigod
and the god realms.
And um
it's not some self-existent place. It's
right here in this room. We're not
talking about a place that is, you know,
you know, 180 km down and 16 km to the
right and then make a short left and
you'll enter
that realm.
Um
but in the sense of this idea of karma
and
in the sense of what would it take for
us to realize that renunciation is a
foundation
for getting free
of the wheel.
Uh
it might be a good idea to do a
meditation on a lower realm.
It may be a nice idea to say
uh okay, I you know,
you know, could I do a tonglen on the
beings that are simultaneously at this
moment suffering great great pain.
Um
I used to do a lot of hot yoga, like
Bikram-ish hot yoga.
And
so it's 105° in the
you know, it's like 102 or something.
And you
you sweat.
And um and I used to do a tonglen and I
would imagine all this like water
pouring off my body
would turn into like beautiful rain
in the hot house and cool off the hot
house and and let those people rest from
their agony and their their you know,
they're just their innate suffering. Um
in a way we allow ourselves a deep
renunciation by admitting that there are
these lower realms
and that there are these pleasure
realms.
In a way we can use the practice
of extending our compassion and
extending our renunciation to know
that the uncertainty of of karma can
bring us to these realms.
And so if we could potentially start
embracing the idea of doing a meditation
for them, the seeds would be remarkable
because our compassion would be off the
charts.
To think that these beings are living
simultaneously in the same moment but
having a completely separate reality
than us.
And it's I don't know, it's a practice
and it's in your reading and I thought
I'd mention it because they suggest
that. They suggest to do that. Give
yourself a a good meditation on the
one level of the hell realm
um in order to kind of
bring that
ultimate deep compassion for beings who
are much less fortunate fortunate than
us.
And so,
you know,
um let's go through some of these last
six aspects.
I can't get no satisfaction.
Always want to
always want more than we have. Um
never satisfied.
Yeah. So, Mick Jagger had it right.
Uh I can't get no satisfaction.
Um
it's pretty self-explanatory, right?
we always want something else, right? Um
Say it again?
Yeah, only the good things. Yeah.
Yeah, that's true.
Um
When's the last time you were
unsatisfied?
At dinner?
I don't know. Like I took the wrong
pasta.
Uh you know, there was the gluten-free
soy macaroni and then there was the
non-gluten pesto cheese macaroni and I
didn't know the difference.
And I you know, I was like anticipating
I love pesto and cheese, you know, and
and gluten. And I
you know, and I I took it and it was
like, oh my god.
That's not what I wanted.
Um
it's the little things like that, you
know.
Right? Little unsatisfaction.
Um
but the bigger things are
um
in relationship to our materialistic
reality.
Uh
you know,
there's a statistic.
China is 37%
of luxury goods in the world. 30 of
every Gucci or Louis Vuitton bag that
gets sold in the world,
a third of them or more gets sold in
China.
Um you know, and
a friend of ours had had a bag and she
said, "See this bag?"
And she was just giving us an example.
This cost $20,000.
And I thought, "My god, you know, that
could pay for
the ACIP input center for a year and a
half in Nepal."
And it was like, I can't get over it.
Like it's a piece of leather, then it
has a nice handle, and a little thing
here that may be gold, I don't know.
But it's fascinating that um
I find in China that they've they've
reached a certain place of extraordinary
wealth and materialism,
and it's
I can't get no satisfaction anymore.
It's so cool
because that's the beginning of what?
The search.
The search for something different
that's not going to disappoint them.
Uh
because you can only put so many of
those in your closet and
impress your friends.
Um
and you could go to the black market and
buy the fake Louis Vuitton for $29.95.
And I I don't Can people tell the
difference? I'm not I'm not sure.
Um
but in any event, I think
we are unsatisfied to some degree about
ourselves in our personal life and
that's a part of life, but we can change
that, too.
Right?
Next.
Yeah, this is a
another depressing
moment.
So, we Yeah, we we die over and over
again.
And once we cross the veil, we forget
everything we ever learned. Now, that's
depressing.
Like all of the ACI training that we're
about to embark on is going to like
vanish at the point of the
you know, last breath.
That we're going to have to re-navigate
back to Diamond Mountain
without a single trace of
remembrance on how
we got to this place.
Um
That's just so depressing.
Why do we want to do?
Get out now.
Get out now as soon as possible. So, the
other thing that's interesting is that
we have such beginningless time
experiences of our death.
Right?
Hold on, Steven, and then like we've had
we've died and shucked off bodies the
size of these mountains, piles of them.
Uh birth and rebirth, every realm of
existence we've had some taste of it.
We've experienced them.
Um
and so
what can we do?
Well, we certainly can learn and
experience the three principal paths.
It's the whole point.
The ultimate Lamrim, right?
Get out and bring everybody with you.
The whole game, get out and bring
everyone with you.
And come back and do it again if you
want to.
Or maybe you don't need to, but that's
where we're going. That's what we have
to do.
Steven.
Can you explain why we don't
remember anything?
Um some people do. I mean
um
I mean I know people who have very clear
distinctions of lives that they've had,
you know, that they actually have the
seeds to to see them.
Um
I I don't I I think uh
you can develop that practice in your
dreams.
A lot of people have lucid dream
experiences of their past lives.
And a lot of people in three-year
retreat had that those experiences. It
was quite clear that they could
tap into the
I don't know, the hard drive of past
lives. The memories are there.
Um but I think the other thing is that
it's a protection device because if we
actually experienced the hell realm that
we were in 16 lives ago,
it would be quite scary.
So, you know, maybe it's also a
protection device karmically to not want
to know
what you know, the last time we were you
know,
I don't know,
uh hacked away
and then revived and done again. So, it
it But I think
there's a real interesting in in past
lives in our time. And I I I think it's
you know, maybe it's valid. I don't
know. I I'm I'm not I don't pursue it,
but I respect people who think that they
could find an answer there.
And there are people that are qualified
to bring you back. I I I don't know
anything about it, but
um
it doesn't matter really because this
moment in time
and the accumulation of beginningless
karma is bringing you to this perfect
moment which is awesome in Diamond
Mountain. The karmas you've accumulated
are ripening right now in a tapestry of
learning more Dharma.
So, wherever you've been, God bless you.
You're here.
Um
it's you know
how many lifetimes did it take for you
to get in this room? Is maybe the
question.
You know, if in the stories of the
Buddha,
you know,
there's so many stories of how many
lifetimes it took him to purify a karma.
You know, like there's a story about a
device of speech thing that it took him
500 lifetimes being a monk to purify
that karma. 500 lifetimes. And that's
something that the correlations get
exponentially unfathomable.
That you know,
if we did extremely bad karma,
how many lifetimes would it take to
finally purify that in the lower realm?
Um
it's much more kind of comforting to
know that you design your future
in this moment and you can design your
future in any way you'd like.
That would be much more comforting.
Um
Why do we have to take our extension of
our own deep compassion for others
and and and and and
swear that we want to save them?
Why? What's the
what's the correlation for us?
Why we why do we want to just get
ourselves out as opposed to bringing
everyone else with us?
We're all in it together, number one.
I mean, we're all in it together, right?
There are only two kinds of beings
according to to our our our philosophy.
Those who are out, ariyas,
and those who are not.
If there's no other
or arhat,
right? There only there there only two
kinds of beings on our planet.
It according to us.
And an ariya is on a on on on their way
out. And an arhat is even closer, if not
on their last moment of life to to get
out.
So,
what does that say?
We're in training to get out.
But the component to get out is really
to to bring others with us
mentally, you know, to think that for
the benefit of others we must do it.
There's no other purpose but for the
benefit of others we must get out.
We must.
And that juice, that motivation,
um will allow us to the the possibility
of coming back and teaching it more and
more and getting more and more
uh
people aware of the fact that they can
get out as well.
But I
I Does anyone
here Do do you know your past life? Is
Does anyone have an experience of it?
Yeah?
Cool.
Was it a good one?
Yeah?
Crying. Aw.
So, it was a hard life?
Yeah.
Okay. You see.
Okay.
That's cool. Next.
We must take birth again and again.
More depression.
Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, think of the pain of it.
Let alone your mom.
But,
you know,
it's just so painful.
I don't have memories of it, but
I don't know.
It must be
you know,
those memories are in there, but I don't
remember, but
the process of going over and over and
over, having births, and then dealing
with this body,
which is high maintenance, right?
Such high maintenance this thing.
Unbelievable how much we pour into this
thing.
You know, the consumption of it. Um
And we know a lot of beings that are
friends of ours around the world don't
have the privilege of having three meals
a day.
We don't
Everyone in this room, I can guarantee
you will have at least 10,000 meals in
your in your fast forward over the next
few years. It's guaranteed. You
You're not thinking about next Friday's
dinner, are you? Because you know, it's
guaranteed. You planted the seeds.
That's not the case in a lots of parts
of the world. That's just doesn't
It's not
the case.
So, it's very beautiful, you know, we we
we have the sustainability of also what?
Leisure and fortune, it's called.
We have it.
It's it's part of who you are. You You
earned it. You gained it. You did it.
We're sitting in a room.
Peop- Beautiful beings are feeding us
three meals a day.
We have time to meditate and study and
do yoga.
It's just amazing. It's a miracle,
actually.
You know, it's a totally a miracle.
It's just
It's not ordinary or normal.
But we think it is.
We take it as normal, and it is not.
It's
extraordinarily
amazing.
Amazing.
So,
yeah, we have to learn it again and
again.
Number five.
Yeah, relentlessly changing. Constantly
changing status. Fortunes go up and down
over and over again.
Um
You've probably heard this story, but I
I'll tell it again.
Mhm.
I I told my my
uh
students today we we were kind of
off
off course on some ideas.
But in 2000, I quit my job.
And uh I was living in New York.
And um I had worked for a company for 21
years. I mean, that was one of my jobs,
but it was a career job, and
um
and I you know, it was a good company. I
had a what they call a a pension plan or
a retirement plan.
Uh and I just threw money at it, you
know, I just threw money in it, and
I thought I met Geshe Michael, and
basically he said, "You need to do this
thing called ACI P." And I said, "Okay,
I'll do it."
And
um I quit.
At the age of 49, I like that's it. I'm
I'm done.
And so the company said, oh, you know,
you have all this money
that you've accumulated and you need to
move it and we can't manage it anymore
and you take it and find somebody to
invest it and I did and it was a student
of mine in New York who was working for
a financial house called Merrill Lynch.
Who I think are gone now. They're bought
by some bank.
And so
I was now in the process of doing
retreat and I I had a opportunity to do
a 30-day retreat. And I, you know,
closed my house in New York, went up to
the Berkshires actually and did a
beautiful 30-day retreat. It was my
first real retreat. And came home to
like all my mail and I'm going through
my mail
and I opened up the Merrill Lynch
statement and
there was like nothing left of my
account.
Nothing. It was like about a thousand
dollars out of this remarkable amount of
money I thought, you know, I knew I had.
And
it was this bubble that burst in the
tech companies in 2001. Everything
crashed and I owned all of those stocks.
Every single one of them. I owned World
Wide Telecom and I owned Enron and I
owned all of them and he put me into all
these stocks and I'm looking at this
thing and saying, you know what, I have
to go back to work. Like
Oh my god, but I something happened
where I wasn't even upset. I was like,
okay.
Karma.
I must have really screwed over people
financially.
And he was waiting for me.
You know, to come home.
And he called me and he just he was
devastated. And I was I was angry, but I
wasn't like I you know, okay, I'm a big
boy. I lost my whole pension plan.
Um,
and he apologized and I said, "Look, you
know, that's just unbelievably
you know,
you know, just irresponsible. You put me
into all these stocks."
So did like 100
50,000 other people in New York lost
everything. It wasn't like I was the
only one. Pension plans in California
just died. It was just horrible.
And I I just accepted it and I thought I
can consult and take take that. But then
he said, "You know, I'm going to pay you
back every penny."
And I said, "Forget it.
You don't have to. I you know,
I'm a big boy. I know what I did. Don't
worry. End of story. But I'm not going
to use you ever again."
And so
so the karma was like, "Okay, you know,
I got enough for a year, but I better
get my butt on the street and start
looking for work."
And um,
6 months later, I get a check in the
mail for $70,000.
And it's from my friend Jay and he's he
just said, "Look, this will take a
while, but here's your first
installment. It'll take about 5 years."
And
I put it in the drone. I called him and
I said, "I'm not cashing that. That's
ridiculous. You don't have to pay me a
penny."
And he said, "Look,
cash it.
I want you to have it and it's just what
I want to do."
And he did that for 5 years, every 6
months.
And
that was a good karma, right?
Boom! It was very cool. And
but there it is, right? Right there.
Like voila. I you know, I had to lose
everything and then boom, back. It came
back in a different way karmically.
And I lived on that money for seven or
eight years in New York.
And it allowed me to do ACIP. So, the
ups and downs of life and the constant
change of our health, the constant
change of our emotional well-being or
not well-being, the constant change of
our relationships
Come on. It's up and down and inside out
all the time.
It's the funhouse at the carnival when
it comes to town. So,
it's always changing. Next.
Yeah. So, uh
John Lennon wrote a song um called
Instant Karma, I think.
And one of the lines is like
you can't take nothing with you but your
soul.
And it's the same thing, right? You must
lose everything and you can only take
your suitcase full of karmic seeds.
Um
You know, people that are in uh
you know, um
I don't know, hospice care are really
amazing because they see the process of
dying.
And I've only done it a couple of times
and
I my aunt was 95 and I went to to be
with her. I was kind of her
you know, they she she didn't have kids
but I was very close to her.
And uh I stayed in her room for like
five nights before finally she passed.
And I couldn't get over the neighbors
who were in the same circumstances that
were had five or six or eight weeks to
live or a to live or whatever.
And there was so much there was the guy
next to her was so angry.
So angry.
That he was dying.
And he was yelling at his children and
yelling at his wife and he it was just
oh my gosh, you know, this is
this is horrible. It was just such a
reality check that
that moment in time when your seeds are
just dropping your life away.
Your body is collapsing. Your
you know, your mind is completely in a
different state. Um
is this kind of situation.
Because there's nothing that you can
take with you.
Uh
except your beautiful seeds.
You see.
And that's what we're here for. We want
to create.
You know, this is a projecting karma
that's the ultimate important one of our
our careers.
And can we do it now?
Yeah.
We can do it now.
We know how to do it now. That's your
next 18 courses.
We'll teach you how to do it before you
have to do it.
It's going to happen to you in your
future.
We
we figured it out. And it'll work.
And you can try it. And guess you
Michael's already doing it to you.
We did it a few years ago here. He gave
you a great meditation practice on
death.
So
um
yeah.
That's the last one.
Um
So renunciation, I'm tired.
Right?
It sprouts in a person's heart once he
has meditated on the torments of life
a sense of profound renunciation
and comes only when you feel the total
disgust even for the supposedly good
things of this revolving life.
When you meditate
and when when you've meditated thus and
feel not even a moment's wish for the
good things of this cyclic life, then
you begin to think both night and day of
achieving freedom
you've found renunciation.
And so
and it doesn't mean that you give your
house and car away.
It doesn't mean that.
You have to it's here and here. It's in
your heart. It's not about
you know
I don't know
giving everything away. You don't have
to do that.
Renunciation is a state of mind. It's a
state of love and it's a state of deep
commitment
to begin the process
of getting out.
And renunciation is really the special
cause that brings you to what we call
great compassion.
It's really the the the the fully
engaged
aspect of the link to to really open our
hearts up to the capacity we're we're at
now and the capacity you will have in a
year, 5 years, 10 years.
Questions?
Any questions?
No. Yes. Maybe.
Yes? No?
Uh yes, sir. Juan has a question.
Yeah.
Yeah, Juan.
You got a suntan, man. You look amazing.
Yeah.
Mhm.
Haha.
Oh, you mean you don't matter? Like you
don't you don't need to get in line
because it's already taken care of and
they've got the whole thing
Yeah.
It's kind of like you're seeing them as
self-existent Buddhas that are
you know, are are basically in it you
know, for themselves in a way.
Well, come on.
Well, let's relate it to our reality of
this current the current reality that
you experience in the world. Does it
look like you don't you're not needed?
Mhm. I think so, right? I mean,
you know, if if that's the case and
you're needed and
there is the possibility that the only
person who can do that is you
for this particular, you know, moment in
time,
uh you must do it.
Because I'm not seeing my world the way
I ideally want to see it.
And that to me is the ultimate, you
know, example of changing my seeds to
change the world to see it
be essentially much more, um
evolved.
You Geshe Michael says we're the last
planet in the solar system. Like they're
waiting for us. Like it's just like
we're the candy cap children.
We didn't haven't gotten it yet.
And to some degree the metaphor
functions. I mean, I I I want to believe
that we, you know, we have
all the capabilities in this body and
mind to do it.
And if it's just doing it for the
benefit of the current dilemma that we
see, that I perceive in our world, then
I must try.
I must. And they're there waiting for
you to help them. It's not like
that you know,
they know what your you know, if you're
beginning less and they know your past
and your present and your future.
Right? They know pretty They probably
know like you know, give them another
like 20 years.
He'll be with us or something. It's
already
They already know that about you.
Um we must, you know,
become the fullest evolutionary
possibility of this human body and mind.
There's
There's nothing to do other than that.
Because then,
you know, the the potential for you,
the potential is exponentially
impossible to even have our minds get it
get around it.
The idea that the possibility of an
omniscient mind
uh emanating countless bodies in
probably in this room
for us to perceive as people that are
helping us get out.
Don't you want to be a part of that?
Yeah.
I think so and maybe
you're suspicious enough to think that
that question was for
me to give some kind of an answer for
everybody to hear or something.
One of the things that I said earlier
today was that in the Sutra system, our
enemy is to have things look
self-existent. It's the curse of our
dilemma.
That
But in the esoteric system, it's to see
things as ordinary. It's the curse.
It's the thing we must remove.
And
we have to begin that practice. It's not
something that is hardwired. We have to
change the seeds to get a taste of when
it doesn't become normal.
And that, you know, a question like that
is not normal.
You know, it gets you thinking that, you
know,
then do I sit back and there's really
nothing that I have to do?
No.
Uh
we must see the extraordinary
possibility of a fully evolved mind of
an enlightened being.
That's the peak of evolution for this
human body and mind.
And we know how to do it.
So,
uh we we must say
that ordinariness
be it has to be killed. We cannot allow
it to be a part of our normal day of
ordinary life. We must see the
extraordinary nature of every day.
The precious, beautiful nature of every
single day of our life. What can happen
today?
You know,
who can I meet? What practice should I
do this morning?
How can I apply it to my all-day mindful
mind of meditation that I had in the
morning? Can I bring it to the world?
Can I practice it?
Can I help others skillfully?
It's just the mission of what we're all
about.
So, I
Thank you.
Anybody else? Oh, boy.
I only have 8 minutes.
Yes.
Um
I have a question about direct
perception about the cheetah.
Yeah.
So, I
just um
um
Well, it it it's in correlation with the
direct perception of emptiness and it
happens directly after.
Uh when the four Arya truths are
self-realized
which are really 16 and they're all
self-realized. And you actually have the
experience of
this you know, this
ray the these these beautiful golden
rays of light, you know,
coming
out of you
out of this deep deep
beautiful love.
And so it
it's the
other side of the coin when you come off
come down off the direct perception of
emptiness.
And that's the second part part B of the
direct experience of Bodhicitta.
Uh can you get tastes of it? Absolutely.
There's definitely taste in deep
meditation.
Real tastes. Um
you know,
that you can take
bank on.
Um
It's not like it's just but it's not
when you have that experience
uh it doesn't go away. That's the
difference.
It doesn't go away. It's it's there for
the rest of your life.
So,
um
there's so many different explanations
of Bodhicitta, you know, and I don't I
don't know them all, but I can say that
uh
in our practice of becoming um
practitioners and having the wish to
gain bodhicitta
and do that in our in our meditation,
uh you should be feeling a subtle
difference of how you express your
yourself to the world.
There should be a a you know a an
expression of oh my gosh, I am not the
same person I was a year ago, and my
possibility of expanding to others has
gotten bigger.
It you know, it it's wider, and my heart
is more open to helping others
and seeing the suffering of others
um more than myself.
And that's that's part and parcel of the
evolution of our practice.
Um
and it you know,
you get those tastes in through your
retreat. It's very sweet.
Um
they say it is like the
the it cracks open. This They say in uh
some Buddhist systems the the the the
iron vase cracks open, and it starts to
pour out of you. Um
and you can have that in a in a good
retreat. You can have a taste of it.
And then you know how to navigate back
to it.
You get you know how to go back and see
if you can do it again and again and
again.
Yeah.
Okay, one more.
Two more, maybe. I don't know.
And what if
a person
saw
uh see the emptiness there and
and
see that
uh that need um
two or three rebirths
to become Buddha.
What will happen in his or her next
life?
I mean,
will
Arya remember the experience of
Oh, an Arya.
Yes, they there I think it's pretty
clear that um
an Arya may not really
know
in the early stages of their life.
Um Geshe Michael is very clear about
that. He said, "It's very interesting
when they when they choose the
reincarnation of some great Lama,
the kid is spoiled. He's special. And
he's kind of royalty in the monastic
system. So, he gets spoiled. And you
know, it's like questionable like is he
really the reincarnation of so-and-so?
And but Geshe Michael has said that
suddenly around the age of 15 or 16,
it's like the massive amount of seeds
start opening up. And they embody that
being that they were. And that they're
actually, you know,
he said that about the most recent
Pabongka Rinpoche. When he turned around
16, he was just a you know, a real
character and a jokester. But then he
just got serious and he became such a
great debater and you saw that this
enormous like ripening happened at the
age of 15 or 16 and then it it just took
off.
And that was pretty much like the
clarity that you know, he you know,
the the direct perception of emptiness
can happen again and again to somebody
who's seen it in each life. It's not
like it's just once.
The next life could jump put you back in
there, you see. And
and also in the direct perception of
emptiness, you see when you're going to
get enlightened.
You're actually you actually see that.
You actually experience that.
When it's going to be how many lifetimes
in front of you is it's going to happen.
Yeah.
Thank you then. Thank you very much.
Oh.
One more. Okay.
Okay.
Yeah.
Left what? Was Yeah.
Yes.
Wow.
Yeah.
Yeah. I
you know, that's something that we're
all dealing with.
How to bring up your Bodhicitta and
for me it's uh
it's meditation. It it really is like uh
you start with, you know,
tonglen. I mean,
start with one human being who is in
pain and suffering. And we all know that
one human being who is in emotional pain
or physical pain or mental pain.
You start there and you
you know, you embody the feeling that
you can help them deeply. And you
literally are in investing in
imagining to take their pain away and
destroying it.
That must give you a result of wanting
to help the suffering of beings. That
must give you a full-on seed to even see
that person get better, but even more so
to have your heart open to the fact that
you can help those
and more than just one.
So, that's just a a single example,
right? We underestimate the power of
that practice. It's It was a secret
practice for many, many years and it and
now is kind of open.
But it has the power to
understand emptiness of the possibility
of your seeds
deeply wanting to help them, your seeds
changing to see them improve or get
better.
And so, that's a start.
And we start uh Shanti Davis says,
"Start with potatoes and carrots.
Don't start with, you know,
um
you know,
I don't know,
you know, thinking that you can save
6,000 people from starvation.
Um start small and then build on it and
then use the practices that are related
to bodhicitta
in your meditation. And then take it
into the world.
Do little things for people who you
understand may have some problems.
Little seeds matter.
And we must learn that the the the
rejoicing of the tiny seeds we do all
day long that we don't accredit
ourselves with.
Having giving somebody a cup of tea or
opening up a door or any of these tiny
little things, we must
like
make them, you know,
bigger cuz they they can generate
something deeper in our hearts for
bodhicitta.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.